Guide to the Miles Bronson Family Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Miles Bronson Family papers
1831-1883
RG 282
Yale University Divinity School Library
4
(10 boxes)
The collection documents the work of Miles Bronson and his family, American Baptist missionaries serving in Assam, India from 1836-1879.
Bronson family
Biographical / Historical
Miles Bronson was born in Norway, New York, July 20, 1812. He graduated from Hamilton Literary and Theological Institution (Colgate University) in 1836 and was ordained to the Baptist ministry that same year. On April 29, 1836, he received an appointment from the American Baptist Missionary Union for service in Assam, India.
Ruth Montague Lucas was born in Madison, New York, August 13, 1813. She was educated at Ladies Seminary in Hamilton, New York, and received an appointment for missionary service on the date of her marriage to Miles, September 7, 1836.
After brief terms of service at the mission stations of Jaipur and Namsang, in 1841 the Bronsons were sent to Nowgong. With the exception of visits to the United States 1848-1850, 1855, and 1857-1860; Miles and Ruth remained in Nowgong until 1868. Shortly after Ruth's death in the United States in 1869, Miles returned to Assam and the Nowgong station. He married Frances Studley Danforth* in 1872; and Miles and Frances continued the work at Nowgong. After the death of Frances in 1874, Miles moved to Gauhati. That same year he married Mary Rankin. Miles and Mary remained in Gauhati until 1879, when they moved to Dibrugarh to open a mission station. Shortly thereafter, Miles and Mary returned to the United States where they lived in Eaton Rapids, Michigan. Miles died there, November 9, 1883.
The children of Miles and Ruth Lucas Bronson were: Mary Rebecca, 1838-1903 (married Cyrus Tolman), Maria, 1841-1874 (unmarried), Eliza, 1842-1912 (married Albert Robinson), Harriette, 1844-1929 (married William Gunn), Ann Sophia, 1846-1920 (married John Titterington), Frances Jane, 1847-1849, Martha, 1850 (died in infancy).
The children of Miles and Mary Rankin Bronson were Miles, b.1875, Ruth and Laura, b.1878.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Existence and Location of Copies
6 reels of microfilm
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from Andover Newton Theological School, 2017
Scope and Contents
The Miles Bronson Family Papers, 1831-1883, primarily document Baptist missionary work in Assam, India, 1836-1879. The collection is arranged according to the following categories: journals; essays and poems; sermons and addresses; correspondence; records of the work of the American Baptist Missionary Union in Assam.
The correspondence is business and personal in nature. Details of administration of the Assam mission appear in letters of Miles Bronson and other missionary personnel: Nathan Brown, Milton B. Comfort, Oliver T. Cutter, Appleton H. Danforth, Grell Keeler, Thomas J. Keith, Marcus C. Mason, John N. Murdock, R. Edward Neighbor, Solomon Peck, Edward P. Scott, Annie K. Scott, Ira J. Stoddard, Cyrus Tolman, William Ward. A personal dimension of nineteenth century missionary experience is reflected in the letters of Ruth Lucas Bronson, Frances Danforth Bronson and other women who worked in Assam: Eliza Brown, Harriet B. L. Cutter, Cordelia S. Ward, Susan R. Ward. There is a name index to the correspondence.
The collection contains a small number of mission records. Included in this material are committee reports related to specific issues of mission administration, such as governance of individual mission stations and financial support of missionary work in general.
Arrangement
Series I. Journals
Series II. Essays and Poems
Series III. Sermons and Addresses
Series IV. Correspondence
Series V. Mission Records
Scope and Contents
Miles Bronson Family Papers (RG 282), Special Collections, Yale Divinity School Library
Missions -- India; Bronson, Miles, 1812-1883; Bronson family
- Journals, Series I
  - Ruth Lucas Bronson
    - Entries, including fragments, 1837, no date (Box 1)
  - Maria Bronson, December 15-16, no date
    - Entries, including letter of Maria to parents, 1/24/1854, tied with booklet, [1853] December 28 - [1854] January 13 (Box 1)
    - Entries, including letter of Maria to parents, 11/20/1854, tied with booklet, 1854 October 25 - November 21 (Box 1)
    - Entries, 1854 December 17 - 1855 February 12 (Box 1)
    - Entries, including letter of Maria to Miles, 5/22/1855, tied with booklet, 1855 April 23 - May 24 (Box 1)
- Essays and Poems, Series II
  - Ruth Lucas Bronson
    - "The ocean", 1831 November 26 (Box 1)
    - "An evening walk", 1831 Novoember 29 (Box 1)
    - "Slavery", No date (Box 1)
    - "Lest I should hinder the gospel of Christ", No date (Box 1)
    - "Poem to Miles" (fragment), 1866 January 1 (Box 1)
  - Mary Rankin Bronson
    - "Druidism", 1851 February (Box 1)
    - "Not knowing", No date (Box 1)
- Sermons and Addresses, Series III
  - Arranged by title
    - Undated fragments, No date (Box 1)
    - And now, if you will deal truly…, No date (Box 1)
    - Appearances of Jesus after His resurrection, No date (Box 1)
    - Bible Society address, No date (Box 1)
    - Charge to missionaries, No date (Box 1)
    - Decision to do missionary work, No date (Box 1)
    - Duties and trials that exist between the relation of pastor and people, No date (Box 1)
    - Errors of science, No date (Box 1)
    - Plea for Assam (Address to Tremont Temple), No date (Box 1)
    - Reasons to be faithful, No date (Box 1)
    - Remarks at Nowgong on first arrival after death of Bro. Scott and Mrs. Bronson, No date (Box 1)
    - Sacrament of communion, No date (Box 1)
    - Sacred and responsible work of gospel ministry, No date (Box 1)
    - Sunday school (2), No date (Box 1)
  - Arranged by date and text
    Scope and Contents
    See first folder of subseries for full list of texts preached upon
    - Undated sermons (Box 1)
    - Sermons, 1850 - 1857 (Box 1)
    - Sermons, 1858 - 1871 (Box 2)
    - Sermons, 1872 - [1881] (Box 3)
- Correspondence, Series IV
  See name index of correspondents in first folder of this series.
  - Fragments and incomplete dates
    - unidentified (Bengali script), No date (Box 3)
    - unidentified hand (1 item), No date (Box 3)
    - Barker, Jane (3 items), No date (Box 3)
    - Bronson, Anna (2 items), No date (Box 3)
    - Bronson, Frances S. Danforth (4 items), No date (Box 3)
    - Bronson, Maria (1 item), No date (Box 3)
    - Bronson, Martha (1 Item), No date (Box 3)
    - Bronson, Miles (5 items), No date (Box 3)
    - Bronson, Ruth M. Lucas (6 items), No date (Box 3)
    - Brown, Eliza (6 items), No date (Box 4)
    - Brown, Nathan (3 items), No date (Box 4)
    - Browne, Mary L. (1 item), No date (Box 4)
    - Champlin, Sarah (1 item), No date (Box 4)
    - Clark, Mary J. M. (2 items), No date (Box 4)
    - Cole, Mary Lucas (1 item), No date (Box 4)
    - Cross, Edmund B. (1 item), No date (Box 4)
    - Cutter, Harriet (3 items), No date (Box 4)
    - Cutter, Oliver T. (2 items), No date (Box 4)
    - Danforth, Appleton H. (9 items), No date (Box 4)
    - Gunn, Harriette Bronson (2 items), No date (Box 4)
    - Gurney, Albanus K. (l item), No date (Box 4)
    - Kay, Sardohka P. (l item), No date (Box 4)
    - Keith, Thomas J. (7 items), No date (Box 4)
    - [Lindeman, B.] (1 item), No date (Box 4)
    - Lucas, Alice (1 item), No date (Box 4)
    - Mason, Marcus C. (2 items), No date (Box 4)
    - Mason, Orrell Keeler (18 items), No date (Box 4)
    - Osgood, Seward M. (1 item), No date (Box 4)
    - Scott, Anna K. (7 items), No date (Box 4)
    - Scott, Edward P. (1 item), No date (Box 4)
    - Tamod, Bogee Emily (1 item), No date (Box 4)
      English translation available
    - Tolman, Cyrus F. (1 item), No date (Box 4)
    - Tolman, Edward (1 item), No date (Box 4)
    - Tolman, Mary Bronson (1 item), No date (Box 4)
    - Usborne, Henry (1 item), No date (Box 4)
    - Ward, William (13 items), No date (Box 4)
    - Whiting, Elizabeth (1 item), No date (Box 4)
  - Arranged by date
    A full list of items is available in the first folder of this subseries.
    - Including from Harriet Lathrop to Ruth Lucas; from Sherburne, New York, 1832 November-December (Box 4)
    - Including from Harriet Lathrop to Ruth Lucas; from Sherburne, New York, 1833 April - September (Box 4)
    - Including from Harriet Lathrop to Ruth Lucas; from Hamilton, NY, 1834 March - October (Box 4)
    - Including from Harriet Lathrop to Ruth Lucas; from Sherburne, NY, 1835 May - November (Box 4)
    - Including from Harriet Lathrop to Ruth Lucas; from Sherburne, NY, 1836 January - October (Box 4)
    - Including correspondence of Miles Bronson and Ruth M. L. Bronson while in India, 1837 February - November (Box 4)
    - Including correspondence of Miles Bronson and Ruth M. L. Bronson while in India, 1838 January - October (Box 4)
    - Including correspondence to/from Miles Bronson and Ruth M. L. Bronson while in India, 1839 January - September (Box 4)
    - Including Ruth to her family and Miles to "the Board", 1840 June - September (Box 4)
    - Including correspondence of Miles Bronson and Ruth M. L. Bronson while in India, 1841 January - November (Box 4)
    - Including correspondence of Miles Bronson and Ruth M. L. Bronson while in India, 1842 March, August (Box 5)
    - Including correspondence of Miles Bronson and Ruth M. L. Bronson while in India, 1843 March - November (Box 5)
    - Including correspondence of Miles Bronson, Ruth M. L. Bronson, and Eliza Brown, 1844 March - December (Box 5)
    - Including primarily correspondence of Ruth M. L. Bronson and Eliza Brown, 1845 February - December (Box 5)
    - Including correspondence of Miles Bronson, Ruth M. L. Bronson, and Eliza Brown, 1846 January -December (Box 5)
    - Including correspondence of Miles Bronson and Ruth M. L. Bronson, 1847 January - November (Box 5)
    - Including correspondence of Miles Bronson and Ruth M. L. Bronson, 1848 February, October (Box 5)
    - Including correspondence of Miles Bronson and Ruth M. L. Bronson, 1849 February - December (Box 5)
    - Including correspondence of Miles Bronson and Ruth M. L. Bronson, 1850 January - November (Box 5)
    - Including correspondence of Miles Bronson and Ruth M. L. Bronson, 1851 January - December (Box 5)
    - Including correspondence of Miles Bronson and Ruth M. L. Bronson, 1852 January - December (Box 5)
    - Including correspondence of Miles Bronson and Ruth M. L. Bronson, 1853 April - December (Box 5)
    - Including correspondence of Miles Bronson, Ruth M. L. Bronson, and Mary (daughter), 1854 January - December (Box 5)
    - Including correspondence of Miles Bronson and Ruth M. L. Bronson, 1855 January - December (Box 5)
    - Including correspondence of Miles Bronson and Ruth M. L. Bronson, 1856 January - December (Box 5)
    - Including from A. H. Danforth to Miles; from Gauhati, 1857 January - September (Box 6)
    - Including correspondence of Miles Bronson, Ruth M. L. Bronson, and Mary (daughter), 1858 January - October (Box 6)
    - A. H. Danforth to Miles; W. Ward to Miles, 1859 January, December (Box 6)
    - Including correspondence of Miles and Ruth Bronson and W. Ward, 1860 January - December (Box 6)
    - Including correspondence of Miles and Ruth Bronson and W. Ward, 1861 January - December (Box 6)
    - Including correspondence of Miles and Ruth Bronson and W. Ward, 1862 January - December (Box 6)
    - Including correspondence of Miles and Ruth Bronson and W. Ward, 1863 January - December (Box 6)
    - Including correspondence of Miles and Ruth Bronson and W. Ward, 1864 January - December (Box 6)
    - Including correspondence of Miles and Ruth Bronson and W. Ward, 1865 January - December (Box 6)
    - Including correspondence of Miles Bronson and W. Ward, 1866 January - December (Box 6)
    - Including correspondence of Miles and Ruth Bronson and W. Ward, 1867 January - December (Box 7)
    - Primarily to Miles and Ruth, from various correspondents, 1868 January - December (Box 7)
    - Primarily to Miles and Ruth, from various correspondents, 1869 January - December (Box 7)
    - Primarily to/from Miles, including from I. J. Stoddard and F.S. Danforth, 1870 January - December (Box 7)
    - Primarily to/from Miles, including from I. J. Stoddard and F.S. Danforth, 1871 January - December (Box 8)
    - Primarily to Miles, including from I. J. Stoddard, 1872 January - December (Box 8)
    - Primarily to/from Miles, from various correspondents, 1873 January - December (Box 8)
    - Primarily to Miles, from various correspondents, 1874 January - December (Box 8)
    - Primarily to Miles, including from R. E. Neighbor, 1875 January - December (Box 8)
    - Primarily to Miles, including from R. E. Neighbor, 1876 January - December (Box 9)
    - Primarily to Miles, including from R. E. Neighbor, 1877 January - December (Box 9)
    - Primarily to Miles, from various correspondents, 1878 January - December (Box 9)
    - Primarily to Miles and Mary Bronson, from various correspondents, 1879 January - December (Box 9)
    - Primarily to Miles and Mary, from various correspondents, 1880 January- December (Box 9)
    - Primarily to Miles and Mary, from various correspondents, 1881 January - December (Box 9)
    - Primarily to Miles and Mary, from various correspondents, 1882 January - December (Box 9)
    - Primarily to Miles and Mary, from various correspondents, 1883 February - May (Box 9)
- Mission Records, Series V
  Records concerning the work of American Baptist Missionary Union in Assam
  - Miles Bronson, Draft of circular letter concerning the Nowgong mission school, 1843 August 25 (Box 10)
  - Miles Bronson, Circular letter concerning Nowgong Orphan Institution, 1847 October 1 (Box 10)
  - Nathan [Brown], Farewell address to the Bronsons, circa 1848 (Box 10)
  - Miles Bronson, Circular letter concerning subscription for erecting a native chapel and permanent buildings for Nowgong Orphan Institution, 1850 July 8 (Box 10)
  - Floor plan of mission house at Nowgong, circa 1851 (Box 10)
  - Miles Bronson, Committee report concerning "The state and claims of Nowgong as a mission station, together with the adjoining tribes", circa 1853 (Box 10)
  - Miles Bronson, Remarks concerning circular letter of Nathan Brown, 1854 October (Box 10)
  - Miles Bronson, Committee report concerning "The language or languages to be employed in communicating the gospel to the Assamese and Hill tribes", 1854 [November] (Box 10)
  - Miles Bronson, Draft of circular letter concerning financial arrangements for additional construction to the Bronson's house, 1856 (Box 10)
  - Miles Bronson, "Substance of Bro. Danforth 's remarks on the present state of the mission", 1856 September 23 (Box 10)
  - I. J. Stoddard, Report of Garo mission, 1868 February (Box 10)
  - Miles Bronson, Papers concerning sale of the printing press, circa 1876 (Box 10)
  - R. E. Neighbor, Report of meeting of Bronson, Mason, Gurney and Neighbor, 1877 (Box 10)
  - R. E. Neighbor, "What I think of the circular", 1877 (Box 10)
  - Agreement wLth C. A. S. Muller concerning construction of bungalow at Gauhati; Floor plan of mission house at Gauhati, 1877 (Box 10)
  - Unitemized vouchers (3 folders) (Box 10)